- Hi everyone and welcome
to the first lecture
of our online course on
deep learning systems,
algorithms and implementation.
I'm Zico Kolter, I'm going to
be giving this lecture,
but I'm teaching this course
with my co-instructor,
Tianqi Chen, who will be giving
some of the later lectures.
We're both faculty at
Carnegie Mellon University,
and we're also offering this
course this Fall at CMU.
But we're making all the material public
as part of this online course.
This lecture's gonna
be a basic introduction
to the topics of this course,
as well as cover some of
the logistics of the course.
As such, it's gonna be a bit different
from other lectures where
we'l actually go into detail
about the methods, the
math, the code, et cetera.
This is really just a
lecture with slides in it,
but we're gonna cover a
bit about why this course
might be of interest to you.
Why we think these are
important topics to know about,
and also cover a bit of background
on the logistics and setup of this course.
All right, so as I said, this
lecture really has two parts.
The first part is about
why you should study,
deep learning systems at all.
Why you might wanna take this course.
And the second will be
more about the course info
and logistics.
So let's jump right in and
get started talking about
why you might want to study
deep learning systems.
Now the aim of this
course is to provide you
with an introduction to the functioning
of modern, deep learning systems.
And what that means is,
you're going to learn
about how these things work internally.
You're gonna learn about methods,
like automatic differentiation,
a number of basic neural
network architectures,
optimization, as well as
methods for efficient
operations on systems like GPUs.
This is how these modern
deep learning systems
actually are run efficiently
on modern hardware.
To solidify your understanding,
the main effort that you'll
put in throughout this course
is that through the homeworks,
you will develop the needle library.
Needle stands for the necessary
elements of deep learning.
And it's a deep learning library
loosely similar to PyTorch.
You're going to incrementally
throughout your assignments,
implement many common architectures
and many of the aspects of this
library really from scratch.
So why should you do this?
Why might you want to study deep learning?
And why might you want to
study deep learning systems?
Well, to start off with,
let's answer the easier question first.
Why do you want to study,
or why might you want
to study deep learning?
Now chances are, if
you're taking this course,
you probably already like deep learning
or at least know about deep learning
and probably have a pretty good idea
about why you might want to
study deep learning.
But I will give a few
quick examples anyway,
many of which you've
probably already seen,
but it wouldn't really
be a deep learning course
if we didn't start off the first lecture
with some cool pictures about the things
that deep learning can currently do.
So maybe you heard about the
famous AlexNet architecture,
which was developed in 2012,
which performed very, very well
on the ImageNet image
classification challenge.
I need to highlight right off the bat,
this is not a history of deep learning,
nor is it assigning credit to any sort of
first elements that, first
architectures of deep learning,
that's an argument I
do not wanna get into.
But this was a very,
very famous architecture
that really at least as a
field and as a technique
in the public view
really did turn a corner
on availability and power of deep learning
by essentially building an architecture
that could classify images
into one of 1000 classes,
much better than standard
computer vision techniques
at the time.
You probably also heard
about the AlphaGo system,
which was developed in 2016
and defeated, not quite the
world champion, I guess,
or number one, but a very, very
highly ranked, essentially,
one of the world's best
players at the game of Go.
Now the game of Go for a
long time was viewed as
a grand challenge for
computer play of games
because the number of possible
moves at each location
is very, very large
and standard techniques
like those used in chess, just
weren't very applicable here.
But using techniques from deep learning,
this team at DeepMind was
able to build a system
that could defeat essentially at the time,
one of the best players in the world,
and soon after all the best
human players in the world,
much, much faster than I think anyone
in the field really expected it to happen.
Maybe you've also heard or
seen about images like these,
these are images of faces
generated by the StyleGAN system,
and I know we're all used
to seeing these things now,
we're actually quite used to seeing faces
that are not real, we
see them everywhere now.
But I remember when this post
was first made on Twitter,
people were advertising
this paper on Twitter
and I thought people were joking.
I thought, actually, this
was just a set of pictures
from the training set that
people were joking about
and saying they were generated by the GAN,
by the adversarial network.
But no, they really were, right,
these are actually fake images
generated by this network.
And I think that we almost
take it for granted now
just how easy it is to generate
pictures of fake people,
which was a capability we did not have
four or five years ago.
A little bit more recent history now,
you've likely heard
about the GPT-3 system.
This is a system built by
OpenAI that can generate text
and the way it generates text
is it essentially writes text
one word or one token at a time.
So given all the previous
tokens in a sentence,
it predicts the next one
and then it adds that,
appends that to the text,
and predicts the next one.
And from this very simple seeming process,
we are nonetheless able to
generate amazingly complex
and coherent pieces of text just from
essentially a deep learning system
that's meant to predict
really a distribution
over next possible tokens in text.
And in fact here, it
hopefully it's legible
in the video here, but this,
I actually asked GPT-3
to write a summary of this course,
and it spit out a very reasonable summary
of a deep learning course.
In fact, it's actually a very
bad summary of this course,
because it's says, we're
gonna talk about the theory
and the math and then we're gonna cover
unsupervised learning and
reinforcement learning.
But it would be a very good
summary of a kind of generic
deep learning course that will
be offered that is offered,
in fact here and will be offered
at many, many universities.
You've also probably seen AlphaFold
and the AlphaFold 2 system.
This is a system that predicts
the 3D structure of proteins
from their DNA sequence.
This for a very, very long time
has been a grand challenge in biology,
understanding how DNA
sequences form the 3D structure
of proteins that actually
carry out tasks in the body.
And for a very, very long time,
this is a chart here of
the progress and accuracy
of these systems over many years
at sort of a well known competition
on this task of protein
folding prediction.
And over the course of four years,
this system, AlphaFold built by DeepMind,
again, was able to really
produce a amazing breakthrough,
amazing scientific
breakthrough in the quality
and accuracy of this prediction
to the point where effectively
you could argue that at
least in some restricted cases,
this problem is in fact
effectively solved.
And finally, it wouldn't be 2022
if I didn't include a picture of
an image generated by
a deep learning system.
This is a picture generated by
the Stable Diffusion system,
which actually was released
like a week and a half ago.
In fact, it was released on the same day
we announced, we also posted the video
announcing this public course,
so they really stole our thunder here.
Of course, this also
relates to the work done
by the DALLE-2 system
and going back for the
DALLE system and many papers before then.
But these systems are amazing
in that they can take
a text prompt and generate,
that probably no one has
ever really thought of before,
and generate a very realistic
painting in many cases
or image in many cases that
corresponds to that text.
So here I wrote the text
prompt of a dog dressed
as a university professor
nervously preparing his first
lecture of the semester,
10 minutes before the start of class.
I don't know why I would've
thought of that thing,
you can imagine it yourself.
And it was an oil painting on canvas
and you see what the system generated was,
well, it looks like a dog
dressed as a university professor
preparing a lecture, I guess
10 minutes before class,
that part maybe is
evident in his expression
and it looks kinda like an oil painting.
And this is just so amazing,
the capabilities that we
have in these systems.
Now one thing you may notice about
all these examples I give, except the very first one,
is that they're all done
essentially at companies,
not actually the last one.
So Stable Diffusion actually is done
at a relatively small company,
but they still have a
fair amount of resources
that were behind this effort.
And the other point I wanna make though,
is in case you're a little
bit concerned saying,
oh, all this stuff is just
happening at big companies.
What can one person or
a small group of people
really do to influence this?
I would, first of all, point to that
first paper and Stable
Diffusion paper actually
is bookend examples of
what a few people can do
with the right methods
and the right cleverness.
But I wanna highlight a few examples too,
of smaller efforts that
I think have still been
amazingly impressive at shaping
the field of deep learning.
So the DeOldify work
essentially done by two people
is more or less, or was, I
believe still is more or less,
a state of the art technique
for taking old pictures,
old photographs in black and white
and creating color versions of these.
Now image colorization has
been researched as a topic
for a long time, but this system
really is an effort of a few people
that ultimately achieves,
I think the visually best
version of this sort of task
that I have seen from this.
Done essentially by two people
with very limited resources,
at least in the initial versions.
If you work in computer vision these days,
you've probably heard of
the PyTorch image models
or timm library.
This is essentially work by one person
that wanted to implement a whole bunch of,
with some help now, but at
least starting out one person,
Ross Wightman, who wanted
to implement a whole lot of
deep learning image classification models
from many, many papers
and test them all out
on benchmark data.
And in many cases using
pre-trained weights
from those papers or many cases,
training them from scratch.
And this has been, started at least
as a relatively small effort by one person
and has become really the dominant
image classification library
that we all use academically
when we are building these vision systems.
And finally, I won't highlight
these other ones actually,
because these in fact
are community efforts,
but there's been many other
examples of libraries,
systems, big, big sort of code endeavors
that are essentially community driven
and that they are for both
libraries and frameworks
that have been community
driven that have really driven
the field forward.
And I'll actually mention
some of these again
when I introduce briefly my co-teacher
in this course, Tianqi.
So all of this that
I've talked about so far
probably is not news to you.
If you're watching this, you
probably say, yes, I get it,
deep learning is great, that's
why I'm taking this course,
that's why I'm listening
to this video so far,
if you haven't skipped forward already.
But why should you learn
about deep learning systems?
Why do you actually want to
study deep learning systems?
Not just deep learning,
but the actual architectures behind
that enable these systems
and the way I'm going to motivate this
is I'm going to show a chart
here of a Google Trends chart
of the interest measured
somehow in deep learning,
the term deep learning over
the past 15 years or so,
14 years.
And I'm gonna annotate this chart
with a few events of note.
So in the late 2000s,
this is actually when the
field of deep learning
in some sense took off academically.
So I was going to conferences at this time
and I remember at
conferences like NeurIPS,
this deep learning became a thing,
a field where there were lots
of papers in it every year
in the late 2000s.
But still, maybe this is always
how academic work happens.
Still, there wasn't much as measured
by Google Trends relative
to the current day.
There wasn't a whole lot of
interest in deep learning,
it was just sort of an
academic trend like many others
that you've probably not heard of
because they were 15 years old
and no one's using them anymore.
Then in 2012, as I mentioned,
the AlexNet network was
released, which again,
this is not a history of
the field of deep learning,
and I've of course should also mention,
though I should, of course mention that
the actual mathematics of deep learning
and neural networks goes
back well into the 80s
and probably before then to the 70s,
this is just a sort of
recent history, of course.
And again, I'm only
annotating a few events,
not trying to make claims
about who was first to do what,
et cetera, it's a game
I don't wanna play in.
But the AlexNet was a
very popular architecture,
yet still, and there started to be a little uptick
in interest in deep learning,
but still not too much happened.
So state of the art performance
on image classification
and still not too much happened.
So then what happened?
When did this start to really take off?
Well, a few other things
happened in the later years.
So in 2015, in 2016,
some libraries like Keras
and TensorFlow and PyTorch
were released.
And if you actually look at the timing
of when deep learning
became truly popular,
it coincides much more with
the release of these libraries
than the actual sort of what we think of
as some of the big notable
papers or events in the field.
And so I kind of wanna
make the controversial,
but maybe not that controversial claim
that the single largest driver
of the widespread adoption
of deep learning has been the creation
of what essentially amounts to,
easy to use automatic
differentiation libraries.
Now that's a little bit
too simplified, of course.
The actual deep learning systems,
which we're gonna talk
about in this course
involve much more than
automatic differentiation.
But this core technology,
which again goes back to the 70s,
not a new technology,
but the widespread avail,
and there were frameworks before that.
So before PyTorch, there was Torch,
just not many people used it,
because you had to learn
a whole new language
called Lua to implement your models there.
So the availability of
Python based frameworks
that lets you quickly
prototype new architectures,
new models.
This I think was the single biggest driver
of the explosion of
interest in deep learning.
Now one thing you may also
see from this chart is
maybe we're in bad territory recently,
maybe something's happening recently.
I don't think it is I think,
there's often issues with
sort of the latest data
in Google Trends.
But more than that, I think
probably was also happening
is that a lot of these
things are just now falling
under the umbrella of AI,
which I will try to avoid that term,
I'll try to be specific
about deep learning
as much as possible.
But probably a lot what's happening,
is people are just using the term AI
to talk about a lot of these things
and not the term deep learning always.
So another way of sort of
emphasizing this exact same point,
I'm actually going to reference
of story from Tianqi's work.
And he, I actually was quite,
I admit, I was quite late to the game
when it came to deep learning,
despite being around
people that were using it,
some of the pioneers in the field.
I actually didn't start
working in deep learning
until about 2015.
Maybe not surprisingly about when
I could easily prototype stuff.
But Tianqi, he was actually
working on deep learning
back in the day,
back in 2012, when a
lot of these architectures
were first being developed.
And in fact, one of his first
projects as a PhD student
was to write code for ConvNets
that would accelerate
their development on GPUs
this around the same time that AlexNet
and such was being developed
and so he was doing
similar things at the time.
And the figures he gives
is that to implement
really a capable convolution architecture
for image classification
on a data set like ImageNet
at the time, it took him
about 44,000 lines of code
and about six months of coding to do so.
And I'll make this point later,
but Tianqi is a really good coder
and it still took him this long to write
a working deep learning architecture.
Contrast that with today,
today, if you wanna do the same thing,
you would probably have to
write about 100 lines of code
and you could probably
do it in a few hours.
And the reason why is because
of deep learning systems
like PyTorch, like
TensorFlow and now like JAX.
And I think we often
don't fully appreciate
just how much of an enabling factor it is
to be able to iterate this quickly.
We think of deep learning
models as being slow to train
and slow to develop and
especially large ones.
But this is amazingly fast,
we have an amazingly fast
current iteration time
enabled by these deep learning systems.
But this still doesn't answer the question
that I set out to answer, which is,
why should you take this course?
So maybe you agree now that
deep learning systems are great.
Why don't you just use them, right?
You can just use, I'm sure
you already do, right?
You probably use PyTorch,
and TensorFlow and JAX.
Why should you take a course
about how these systems actually work?
And there I actually think
there are three reasons,
I'm going to give for why this course
might be right for you to take
if you are interested in deep learning.
The first reason of course
is, maybe obviously,
if you want to build
deep learning systems,
you better understand them.
So despite the current state
of deep learning libraries
where you may say that, okay,
libraries like TensorFlow
and PyTorch kind of won,
they're the standards everyone uses.
It's actually not really true.
I think actually the field
of deep learning systems
is remarkably fluid as evidenced
by the relatively recent emergence of JAX
as a dominant framework
for a lot of research
in deep learning.
It's a relatively new thing,
this happened the last couple years.
But I don't think we're
done yet in some way,
I think there's actually
a lot of work to be done
in developing new systems,
maybe more specialized systems,
maybe systems that
specialize in some different
area or different paradigm
for deep learning.
But I don't think we're finished with what
the final state of deep learning
systems is gonna look like.
And if you want to develop
your own frameworks
or build upon existing
frameworks and by the way,
all the frameworks out there
essentially are open source,
so you could definitely
just download them,
the source currently and
start contributing to it
if you understand them.
If you want to do all
that, then this course,
and some practice will
prepare you to do this.
So this is maybe the most obvious reason
why you might wanna take this course
if you want to build and
contribute to these libraries
as well.
But that's not the only reason,
and the second reason
for taking this course
is actually the one that I would emphasize
most heavily for
practitioners in the field.
And that reason is,
understanding how the internals
of deep learning systems work
lets you use them more
efficiently and more effectively.
And I really do mean that, right?
So if you want to build scalable models,
efficient models, models
that will execute quickly
or that make full utilization of a GPU,
you really do want to understand
how these systems are
working underneath the hood.
What is really being executed?
How are they translating
your high level description
of a network architecture,
to something that really
executes on hardware
and then trains and
differentiates that system
and adjust parameters and all that.
How does that work and
understanding how that works
will actually enable you
to write more efficient
and more effective code.
And this is especially true
if you're doing research
in deep learning.
So especially if you
are doing things like,
developing new kinds of
layers, new architectures,
new structures in deep learning.
This will be vastly
improved if you understand
the logic and the mechanisms
behind these systems.
I've always kind of referred to
understanding deep learning
systems as a kind of superpower
that can let you accomplish
your research aims
even if your research aims
are not about system building
can enable you to accomplish
them much more efficiently.
This is probably the main
reason why most of you,
I think, can and should take this course.
But I would be remiss if I
didn't add one more reason
to this pile, which is that,
deep learning systems
are really, really cool.
And the reason why these
systems are so much fun
is actually very simple.
And that is, that despite
the seeming complexity
of these things, PyTorch
and TensorFlow at this point
are millions of lines of code.
But despite the seeming
complexity of these libraries,
the core underlying algorithms
behind deep learning systems,
behind quite capable
deep learning systems,
to be honest, are
extremely, extremely simple.
Really the core algorithms behind
every single deep learning architecture,
every single, all of those advances
in machine learning models that you saw
that I put up on those previous screens.
At least algorithmically, they're
all essentially based upon
automatic differentiation and
gradient based optimization,
at least from a mathematical standpoint,
those are the two or handful of algorithms
that actually underlie all of this.
And then on the implementation side,
essentially, they are built
upon efficient linear algebra,
especially efficient matrix
multiplies on GPU systems.
Unlike say an operating system where
if you wanna build an operating system,
you really have to build
quite a bit of code,
you have to write a lot of code.
And so courses on operating systems
that take you through operating systems
and usually build a very, very basic one.
And you have to write, even for that,
you have to write a lot
of code to do anything
at all reasonable.
But you actually could
write and you will write
a reasonable deep learning library,
if you wanna be really
compact with your code,
you could probably do it in
less than 2000 lines of code.
Something that will run on a GPU
that will do automatic differentiation,
that will have operations
like convolutions
and convolution networks,
recurrent networks,
transformers, all this
kind of thing, right.
You can do it in almost no code
because the actual ideas underlying
these systems are simple.
And they're also, and I say this
a little bit tongue in cheek,
but they're also kind of magical.
Before I worked in deep learning,
I sort of was brought up in
traditional machine learning
when we derived all our gradients by hand,
and that was the big
effort you went through
when you derived some new model,
as you wrote out a bunch
of gradients by hand.
I remember the first time I built
an automatic differentiation library
and I realized that I could take,
form some complex expression,
take its gradient and then form
an even more complex
expression of its gradient
and differentiate through
that thing, and do all that
despite the fact that I
actually would really struggle
to even derive that by hand.
I probably could do it,
but it would take me quite
a while to derive this
manually yet I could write
some code that did it.
This is really, really cool.
And it's an experience I think everyone
working in deep learning should have.
All right, so with all that being said,
let me give a little bit
more now boring information
about this course and the
logistics of this course.
First up to introduce myself
and my co-instructor Tianqi.
I am a faculty member at Carnegie Mellon,
I've been there since 2012.
But in addition to working
in industry or at CMU,
I've also done a fair
amount of work in industry.
So I was previously at
a company called C3 AI.
Now I work, I'm a chief
scientist in AI research
at Bosch and the Bosch Center for AI.
And my research in academics focuses on
a lot of techniques for new algorithms
and new methods now in deep learning.
So I've done a lot of work
on adversarial robustness,
I've done a lot of work,
especially certified and provable
defenses against adversarial attacks.
Also done a lot of work in
what we call implicit layers,
these are layers that instead of just
being formed by some sort of stacking
of traditional operations,
you form them by actually solving
a more complex operator like
an optimization problem,
or like a fixed point equation.
And you actually differentiate through
those analytically.
In fact, we'll according to the
current schedule, at least,
if there is time, we will have a lecture
on implicit layers at the
very end of this course.
Implemented, of course,
in our own framework.
I was also an early PyTorch adopter,
and one of my marks of
pride, I'm going to quickly
sort of not hold a candle
to the system's work,
Tianqi has done that, I'm
about to show in a second.
But myself and my group, we
were early PyTorch adopters,
we were actually mentioned
as the first group
releasing third party
libraries for PyTorch.
And one of my claims to fame there is that
as part of our efforts to
release an optimization layer,
so this was a layer, a third party library
that would solve optimization
problems as a layer
in a deep networks like
quadratic programs,
if you know what those are.
And to do so, I wrote a CUDA
kernel as part of PyTorch
that could do batch parallel solving
of multiple linear systems as part of our,
as one step of our optimization solver.
And the real claim to
fame there, of course,
is that in doing so I messed up or rather,
I wouldn't standardize somehow
the matrix striding that PyTorch assumes
coming out of its CUDA kernels.
And I introduced a bug in
PyTorch's linear solver
that I think persisted
for a year after that,
just everyone was so confused
about why this linear solver
would just randomly crash at times.
So that's my claim to fame, I guess,
sadly about deep learning systems.
Now the other instructor
is a bit different.
So Tianqi Chen is also
a faculty member at CMU.
And also in addition to
this has a foot in industry,
so he was the co-founder
of the OctoML company,
which is a company now
does a lot of support
and development for the TVM library.
But the real claim to
fame is the following.
So I'm giving this lecture
so I can suitably embarrass
Tianqi a little bit
in our introduction here.
For a long time, the standard
story I will give about him
is that in deep learning systems
or machine learning systems as a whole,
there really are three
big players in this field.
There is Google, of course,
releasing TensorFlow, JAX
and many other libraries.
There's Facebook, of course from PyTorch,
but also things like Prophet,
a time series library,
and then there's Tianqi.
So Tianqi has been,
he was the original developer of XGBoost,
one of the most frequently used libraries
for gradient boosting and still
one of the most widely used
libraries for tabular data.
He was a lead developer
for the MXNet library,
which was another deep
learning framework like PyTorch
and TensorFlow.
And then most recently, one
of the founding developers
and core developers of
the Apache TVM library.
And so he has done kind of
an amazing number of things
in machine learning systems as a whole,
and actually quite excited
to be able to teach
this course with him.
So before now I jump into
the details of this course
and these lectures, I want
to offer a big disclaimer,
which I think needs to be said here.
And what I'm saying here is
that we are offering this course
online for the first time.
We have not done this before
and a lot of the material,
especially the assignments,
which is the most complex
part of this course
is being revamped from
the previous version.
Actually being revamped,
even for the CMU version
and then that will be they're
kind of beta testing this,
and then you'll be given the
assignments soon after that.
But as par for the course here,
there are, no pun intended,
but as par for the course,
there are going to be bugs in the content
and the assignments, or
just in the logistics
of how we run things, right?
This is the first time we're offering this
as an online course, there
are going to be bugs,
there are going to be
hiccups, please bear with us.
There's a saying that you
get what you pay for, right?
And this course is free,
it's free because we want
people to be taking it
and want this material to be out there.
But we are doing this ourselves
and we are putting it together ourselves
and there will be bugs in it.
So we apologize kind of
ahead of time for this,
please bear with us, we will
do our best to fix these things
and extend deadlines as needed
to account for these bugs,
but they will be there, and we appreciate,
you are all beta testers for
this course as we create it.
So part of the fun of
taking an online course
for the first time is that
you become a beta tester
for the course.
All right, now learning objectives,
what are you gonna learn in this course?
I've probably made this
clear from past slides,
but let me lay it out just in very,
hopefully clear terms here.
If you stay through this whole course,
do all the assignments
and do a final project.
Then by the end of this course,
you will understand the basic functioning
of modern, deep learning libraries,
including concepts like
automatic differentiation
and grade based optimization
from an algorithmic standpoint.
You will be able to implement
really from scratch, right,
because we're talking
about implementing these
without PyTorch or without
TensorFlow behind you,
but just really, just from raw Python,
you'll be able to implement several
standard deep learning architectures,
things like MLPs, ConvNets, RNNs or LSTMs,
various kinds of RNNs,
and then transformers,
and do it truly from scratch.
And you will also understand and implement
how hardware acceleration
works under the hood
and be able to develop your
own highly efficient code.
Now it's not going to be,
I should emphasize it's not
going to be nearly as efficient
as libraries like PyTorch or TensorFlow.
There's still a big gap between
the very best that optimization can do
and that the code optimization
can do, I should emphasize.
And what you can do with 2000
lines of code, no question.
So we're not gonna break
any speed records here,
but you will be able to create libraries
that work on reasonable,
medium sized data,
data like CIFAR, right, reasonably sized
networks and architectures,
you'll be able to develop them,
write medium size architectures
that actually work for these systems
and do it entirely from scratch on GPU
with automatic differentiation, with
nice optimizers, all that.
Now the course website,
which is dlsyscourse.org,
has all this information
and will have a listing
and also posting of all the
lectures for the course.
And you can look at the schedule of topics
to see what you'll be learning there.
Now, one thing to emphasize
is that that schedule,
at least the schedule
here that I'm listing
is the schedule for the CMU version,
which is about two weeks
ahead of the online version.
But we will also post
the dates and the videos
for all the online lectures
as they become available
and it will follow the same structure as
the main CMU course.
Actually only this lecture
has slightly different slides
because there's different logistics
for the online course
versus the CMU course.
But the rest of the schedule
will follow the same schedule
between the CMU version of the
course and the online course
and the schedule is up on the website.
It talks about things like covering
an ML refresher and background,
automatic differentiation,
different types of
architectures, et cetera.
Now one thing you will see
is a lot of the lectures
are broken down between
algorithm lectures,
so lectures covering kind of
the methodological algorithms
or techniques used to solve some
or to accomplish some
task in deep learning,
and then implementation lectures
where we will actually
implement some portions of this
or walk you through
some simple live coding
of how these things actually
are done in practice.
Now in order to take this course,
what should you know ahead of time?
And to be honest about this,
there is some reasonable
prerequisites you should have here
in order to get the
most out of this course.
Now it's not to say that if you
don't have all these things,
the course is impossible.
If you're really excited
about it and want to learn
some of these things concurrently
as you go through the
course, you are welcome to,
just know that it will
be more effort to do so.
But to take this course,
you should have some background
in systems programming.
That means basically C++
coding, how to compile things,
how to compile things like,
not just run Python scripts,
but actually compile executable code
that sort of runs on natively on hardware.
Linear algebra, so you
should be familiar with
vector and matrix notation.
So there's no math, I
mentioned in this lecture,
but later lectures will actually require,
I will write things like a
bunch of matrices and vectors
multiply it against each other.
I will do things like take gradients
or derivatives of these things
and you should know what that means.
That means also, and probably
the biggest requirement
really is linear algebra,
but there's other things too,
like calculus, really, to be
clear, just taking derivatives.
We don't really do any integrals,
there's some integrals
in probability, I guess,
but we don't do many
integrals in deep learning.
But you should know when I write things
like gradient symbols and stuff like that,
you should know what these things mean
or have some understanding of it.
We can provide some links to refreshers
or background material on this,
but if this is really brand new to you,
this could be somewhat challenging
to become familiar with.
As well as sort of basic proofs,
now we're not gonna do
many proofs in this course
to be very clear, this is
really a systems course,
but you should be familiar
with sort of the basic
constructs of how you go about
deriving things mathematically.
How do you derive a gradient
and stuff like this?
You need some Python and
C++ development background
and a common question that's asked,
is how much C++ background do you need?
The answer is, I don't think that much,
we're not using any
advanced features of C++
or anything, we're not even using,
certainly not C++20 and not even C++11
or anything like that.
I don't even know if that's
the right year to be honest.
I don't know those things very well,
we're not using unique
pointers or anything like that.
It's really just C with a
few classes in addition.
So I see this as actually
very minimal C++ experience,
but what you should know how to do is
if we give you a template for
writing a matrix
multiplication call in C++,
so this template would take
in a bunch of float pointers
and const float pointers
and stuff like that.
The sizes of these
matrices, things like this,
where those pointers point
to the raw underlying data
in the in the matrices,
you should know how to write quickly
a matrix multiplication
routine that would multiply
these two matrices together.
And then most importantly,
because this will happen,
when you mess up your indexing
in C++ because there's
no safe indexing there
and you have a segfault of your program,
you should know how to debug it,
either through a debugger,
or if you're like me,
then through at least, the very least
through printf statements that,
this is how I debug honestly, C++ code.
But you should know how to fix things
when your code segfaults, right?
So that's kind of the level
of C++ background you need.
Python, you should probably be familiar
with classes and such in Python too,
because you will be implementing
most of the structure of
this library in Python
and that you have to be familiar with.
But C++ is really sort of
for the low level background.
You don't need to know CUDA
programming ahead of time,
we will cover what you need
to know for the course,
but you need to understand
basic C++ programming.
And then finally you do need
to have prior experience
with machine learning.
If all of this, if machine
learning is really new to you,
you're much better off taking
a machine learning course first
and then taking this course afterwards.
You will get much, much more out of this
if you're already familiar
with machine learning
and probably already
familiar with deep learning,
to a large degree and
then take this course
to understand more how
these things actually work.
So if you are unsure
about your background,
then what I would say is,
take a look at the first three lectures,
I guess not including
this one, the next three,
and look at homework zero,
which is gonna be released
two days after we release,
we officially start the class.
This homework zero is essentially
meant to be a refresher
on some basic ideas of traditional
ways of writing things.
Basically you will implement
softmax regression
and a simple two layer neural network.
And you should be familiar with how,
neural network in using
kind of manual backprop
and you should be familiar with that,
you should have seen this before
and maybe with a bit of refresher,
be able to do that relatively quickly
to know this course is right for you.
And one of these, you
actually will also write C
with a C++ backend.
But if that is very challenging for you,
then probably should
take some other material
before you take this course.
But if all those things
are pretty straightforward
or really can be made more
straightforward again,
if you brush up a little bit,
then this course is likely
the right level for you.
Now there are four main
elements to this course,
the video lectures of which
you are watching the first one,
programming based homeworks,
a final project done in groups
and interaction in the course forum.
And it's important to
take part in all of these
in order to get the full
value of the course.
I really think that
each of these components
plays a crucial, crucial role
in really understanding the material.
Even if, for example,
lectures are not directly
using the homework,
they're still very important to know.
And even if the forum is
in some sense, optional,
it's very valuable to get interaction
with other students taking the course
in order to get the
most out of it possible.
I do want to emphasize that
this online public course
is offered really independently
of the CMU version.
So we can't offer CMU
credit or things like this
for taking this course, even if you pass
and do well on the course.
But what we will do is
for everyone in the course
who completes the assignments,
gets an average of 80% or higher
and submits a final project,
you'll receive a certificate
of completion for the course
to sort of indicate you've completed it.
We'll somehow make it official,
probably post it on the
website or something
so you can have an official
link to it and things like that.
But you will receive a
certificate of completion
personalized to you that in some sense,
certifies you've taken
and completed this course,
even in online, even just, in some sense
in the online public version.
Because it is a lot of effort
and we do want to ensure that
you have something to show
and some sort of record
that you've completed this
and done it successfully.
Now I'll end by just
describing each of these
a little bit in each
of these four elements
in a bit more detail here.
So the video lectures
themselves are going to be
essentially in the format
you're watching right now.
So they will be live
recordings of the lecture,
they will consist of slide
presentations like this one.
But most won't just be this,
I think this is the only lecture
that is just nothing but slides.
The rest will all also have things like
mathematical notes to them, derivations
and in many cases live coding
to illustrate some ideas, okay?
Videos for all the
intellectuals will be posted
to YouTube or other video sites.
We're gonna try to make them available
on a few different video sites
so that they can be accessed globally
according to the course schedule.
And videos will be available to everyone,
so because they're on YouTube
anyone can watch them.
So you can actually watch
without officially enrolling
in the course, many of
you probably are watching
without officially
enrolling in the course.
They don't require
registering for the course.
One thing I will mention,
which you can probably tell from this,
if you've made it this far
through the lecture so far,
is that these lectures
are taken in one take.
We're not doing a lot of editing here.
Essentially, we are recording these live
and we will with minimal
can be cutting at the beginning at the end
or if something really goes
bad cropping in the middle,
we're mostly gonna do these in one take
and with all the hiccups
and such that happen
in a real lecture.
So this is sort of a online version,
but still kind of live stream,
think of them as live streams of lectures.
The second component that I mentioned
was programming assignments.
And this is actually, if I was to say,
this is probably the most
important component of the class.
So in addition to homework zero,
which is kind of a separate
thing in and of itself,
there are four homeworks,
homeworks one through four,
and these four homeworks take you through
the process of building different aspects
of this needle library,
this minimal Python,
deep learning framework.
And in particular, you're
going to first develop
an automatic differentiation
framework for needle.
Then you will use this to build a simple
neural network library
with things like modules
for neural networks,
optimization techniques,
data loading, that kind of stuff.
You will then implement
linear algebra backends
on both CPUs and GPU systems.
And finally, you'll use these things
implement a number of,
in the fourth assignment,
a number of common architectures
like combination networks
recurrent networks
and possibly Transformers.
Each of these assignments
builds on previous ones
and you actually have to
complete them in order,
you have to complete the first assignment
before you can do later ones
because they build on each other.
And this process of building this library
really is the key component of the course
and it is how you will
learn the most through it.
So anyone can watch the lecture videos,
but in order to submit the assignments,
you do need to officially
sign up for the course.
So you have to actually
register for the course,
so if you're watching
this video just on YouTube
and have not signed up for the course yet,
if you want to submit the assignments,
which is really the way
you learn this material,
then you sign up for the course
and you will get an account
to submit assignments to
our auto grading setup.
Now one thing I want to
mention is that the homeworks
are entirely coding based.
There's no derivations, nothing
like this in the homeworks
or whatever derivation we have,
it's sort of implicit because then
you have to code it up afterwards,
to know if it actually works or not.
The homeworks are entirely coding based
and they're all auto graded.
This is actually true
for the CNU version too.
This is the exact same in the
CNU version of the course.
Everything, there's no theory
questions on the homework,
it is just programming
assignments, all code based.
And it's graded through
our own auto grading system
that I've actually been
developing for a few years.
And this auto grading system
works a bit differently
from others you may have seen,
I'll document this a
lot in a future lecture,
actually a separate video
about the auto grading system
I'll post soon after this one.
I'll run to the process of submitting code
to this auto grader.
But the big difference that
I'll just highlight right now
is that in this auto grader,
you actually run all your code locally
rather than submitting
your code and having it run
on the auto grader which
causes all sorts of problems
because the environment
in the auto grader
is never the same as the
one you've coded on locally.
So you actually run all
your execution locally
and you only submit answers.
So the answers and check
against reference solutions
in the auto grading system,
which makes it much more efficient,
much faster to run as
well as sort of makes it
a little bit less painful
in terms of debugging
environment setups.
So I'll go through all that
in a second in later lecture.
It also means that essentially running
in Colab environments, at least currently,
I know Colab's changing monthly,
so we may run into some
issues, hiccups with Colab.
But at least currently you
can do all the assignments
in Colab and submit them,
execute them all in Colab
and do all the auto grading and use that.
And as I said, I will go through that,
the setup and at least
the desired workflow
for how you should do assignments.
I'll go through that in a separate video
in a few, probably posted actually concurrently
with this one, but in
a few more in a days.
All right, the second to last component
is the final project.
So in addition to homeworks,
there will be a final project
and unlike the homeworks, which
are to be done individually,
the final project should
be done in groups.
So you will form groups,
there will be posting on
the forums to form groups
as the time comes then in groups of three,
especially for the online course,
if you wanna find a group of one,
or if you find bigger
groups that's certainly fine
the point is to form a group
and do a final project.
And the idea here is the
final project involves
developing some new piece
of functionality for needle.
So it's kind of homework five,
designing homework five, right?
Well, to be clear, it's
homework zero and homework four,
the homework so you're the final project
is like homework five.
You develop some new
functionality capability
to the needle framework.
It's really important though,
that this final project involves some kind of
extension to needle,
not just implementing some architecture
and certainly not just
implementing an architecture
in PyTorch or TensorFlow.
You can't just do that as a final project,
it really has to be an
extension of the needle library,
add a different kind of
hardware acceleration
to the back end.
Our GPU work is gonna work
on CUDA using CUDA libraries.
So you could do one that uses OpenCL
or maybe optimizes for the M1 Apple chip,
stuff like this, right?
All these things are possible,
or maybe you do sort of
hardware fused optimization
for fused operators and things like this.
These there all potential projects,
we'll also post a few more possibilities.
But the idea is that you
want to do some extension
of needle as your final project.
And finally, the last
thing is the course forum.
So for those who sign up for
the course, and actually again,
this part requires you to
actually enroll in the course.
When you enroll in the course,
you will soon thereafter get an invitation
to join the class forum
where you could log in after this class,
after watching this lecture,
if you haven't done so yet.
And you should use this course forum,
essentially as a resource
to discuss and talk about
the aspects of the course.
You can and should ask
for help, for example,
with assignments in the forum.
We won't be able to answer all questions
that is, we instructors and the TAs
won't be able to answer all of them
just due to sort of availability.
But please do up vote questions
that you find important
and relevant that you are
struggling with maybe.
And we will try to answer the most upvoted
or the most liked questions
to be sure that they're not
sort of widespread issues
that everyone's encountering.
But then also please do
help by answering questions
from other students, right?
We want to form somewhat of a community
around this course here,
so please do not just post questions,
but also see if you can answer questions
from other students.
The more you're able to do that,
the more everyone kind of benefits.
You can ask for help and that does include
in some cases posting code.
But please we have further,
or I should say further instructions
are posted in the main
welcome message in the forum.
But we do have some sort of formal rules,
but the reality is you can do things
like post code and stuff
and you can even share
small amounts of code,
but please be reasonable,
don't just verbatim share entire solutions
on the course forum,
you get the most out of this course
by implementing the
assignments yourselves.
And if you post your code,
then that the makes other people
not able to have that experience,
or they just end up copying the code
and not writing it themselves.
And so be reasonable when it comes
to what you post in the forums,
you can absolutely share
code and share at least
snippets of code and things like this.
Again, it's an online course,
so you could in some sense,
do whatever you want,
but at least in the public forum,
please do be sort of reasonable
in terms of not trying
to give away content
for people that would rather not sort of
see the full solutions
posted for the assignments.
All right, with that,
I'm ending the first lecture
here with a few parting words.
So we're really excited
to be able to offer this course publicly
and we really look forward
to having you in the course.
And if you do have feedback
or comments for us,
please let us know.
Now it may not be possible to make changes
during this offering, but we really want,
we are making this course
public because we want it to be
a resource for those that are interested
in deep learning systems,
or just interested in
deep learning as a whole.
And if you can give us feedback
that can help us improve
at that mission, we appreciate it.
So we look forward to
having you in the course,
as I said, I promise the next lecture
is much more content full.
So if you got through this and said,
hey, where's the, I haven't
learned anything yet,
where's all the content?
Look at the next lecture next,
it will cover some of the
basics of machine learning.
And then soon we'll get into
automatic differentiation after that.
But we really look forward to having you
and we hope you enjoy this course
as much as we're enjoying
putting it together.